Okay.
And good afternoon everybody. And uh for
those who are joining us at this time,
uh we've just admitted everybody from
the waiting room. So we're it does take
a minute or two for everybody to get on
in. And so in the meantime, uh, my name
is Dominic Zerlo and I am with the New
Mexico Department of Health and we are
here, the Department of Health is here
to help assist administratively with the
committees for um, that were uh, started
by the medical psilocybin advisory board
and the chair of this particular
committee is Dr. Larry Leman. Um, and
uh, so with that, Larry, I will turn it
on over to you. And as mentioned, we do
have our staff that are here to help
with muting and unmuting individuals and
with moving uh any uh any technical
issues. We'll be happy to help as we
can. So, thank you very much.
>> Great. Thank you, Dom. Uh good
afternoon, everybody. Good to uh good to
see so many of you here. Uh it's it's
great. We're um I'm just gonna kind of
we'll summarize where we were at the end
of the last meeting. We had you know
agreed on like seven main um um areas of
scope that we're addressing and um those
included everything from training care
plans and uh and such. We had made a
decision that um during each of our
meetings at least for the next few
months till we saturate our own
education that we're going to have
speakers either internally or externally
uh that are going to help present um
information so we can all get that. U I
think I'm going to share a little bit so
that we're going to have Chris Caldwell.
Um Chris is actually a leader of end of
life psychedelic uh you know training.
She's located in Boulder's a professor
at Nuropa. Um she's going to be doing
some focus with us um um in a little bit
little bit later we'll get started. Uh
um and Chris is gonna focus on we talked
some on um the role of like the care
team the facilitators um and role of the
care plan which were two of the major
issues I've had conversations with
people about a several other things that
are planned for future meetings. I'm
going to share those and then kind of
ask people to, you know, suggest what
else do they think would be helpful for
this committee to to people um to get on
the same page. So, we have a plan for
one of our internal uh um members, Jen
Clement, to talk about um psychedelic
chaplain, the role of psychedelic
chaplain. Um James Brown who I see is
here today is going to give a talk at a
later point on um really kind of
pharmarmacological um um issues that are
more common in people that have end of
life issues um cancer um altered
metabolism.
We're um hoping to have actually people
to um talk that are actually working in
of a psychedelic uh doula role to talk a
little bit about how it works to have um
you know multiple people there
potentially in other words partners and
such there um and but we're very open. I
mean we have room for other people to
come speak. So if people have some
thoughts when we um go into the comment
phase in a little bit um love to hear
thoughts on what other areas would be
helpful to us. And again our main focus
is to accumulate the information uh that
we need to make um um additional
recommendations on those uh seven seven
scope areas.
So having said that um um uh I think
it'll work. Can we do public uh can we
do both committee? Here's a question for
for So is there a difference between
public comment and committee comment?
Can you know is there a difference
there?
>> Not really.
>> No, Larry, you can just do that as you
wish. It can either be during the
meeting for this or you can do it at the
end. So that is however you would like
to set it up.
>> Okay. Well, um right now like dur we'll
call this during the meeting. Um, I'd
like to have thoughts on other areas
that would be helpful um for committee
and and public members um regarding uh
regarding end of life care. I mentioned
about four or five things, but I'm I'd
love to hear people kind of raise their
hands and have some other thoughts and
we can we can have those set up. My goal
actually is over the next week or so to
actually set up a little bit of schedule
so you know that. And the idea that
would be probably be about 20 minutes of
each meeting and then that I think
that'll be a good way to sort of spark
conversation and give us some
background. We're also going to have um
one committee member is going to give us
sort of an overview of where programs
are, where research is at. So, we're
going to try to cover those, but I'm
sure there's other areas that I haven't
thought of and would love to hear
people's thoughts.
Okay. And we have a request in the chat
if we could please post the seven
topics.
>> Ken, um, Dom, do you have easy access to
um, uh, to the the PowerPoint that uh,
we did last time?
>> I am going to it right now to get it to
copy and paste.
>> Awesome. Appreciate that. Yeah, just
give me a minute to be able to get that.
>> Thank you, gentlemen. So, again, if you
wish to speak, go ahead and please raise
your hand. That way, we can go ahead and
enable your microphone credentials.
If you are on the Teams app, it'll be a
hand icon that you can select. If you're
on the phone, you'll have to hit the
menu, which could you usually look like
three dots. And if you're joining us on
telephone today, it's going to be star
five.
>> First up is Don.
>> Don, I've enabled your microphone
credentials. You may unmute yourself and
begin when you're ready.
>> There. Is that better? Can you hear me?
>> Yes, sir.
>> Great. I just want to I've got stage
four prostate cancer and right now my
health is pretty well because the
medicine is working. But if this starts
to go, hopefully it won't, but I need I
want to be to
say that it's the mental with
>> that is an issue for those of us that
have cancer. Only imagine if you're
dying
there. This medicine needs to be used
help our mental and emotional
fear of all of this.
We also in my opinion need to figure out
how far
do we start to
I don't want to I guess the word
administer psilocybin to somebody with
cancer who is
coming to the end of life.
>> John this is Larry Leman. Um if am I
unmuted?
>> Yes. Okay. Um I'm going to try to
summarize a little because we had a
discussion of this and I want to share
that with you because it's actually one
of the um uh the these scopes here. It's
the one we say establish definition and
scope for end of life criteria. And so,
you know, the committee hasn't made any
decision, but I can tell you sort of a
the feeling of uh at at the prior
meetings and actually other meetings
that have happened around the state is
that that it's it's this is not focused
on like hospice care and just the last
weeks that have a serious diagnosis um
like stage four prostate cancer. Um I
think most of us myself would view
eligible for that care at the time of
the at the time of the diagnosis. again,
you know, that that's not been written
that settled in stone anywhere. But I
think that that makes sense. I
personally wholly agree with you that
this is really that you want people to
be able to, you know, improve their
mental state, you know, early on during
the during the process. So, I think that
I would say the that from the previous
conversations, um, the committee is was
very supportive of what you're saying,
which is to have it early on. And I
think that's that is what I suspect
we'll wind up recommending.
>> Great. And can I can I make one more
comment? Is that okay?
>> Sure. Go ahead.
>> There is a study being done in Colorado.
I think it's at anes about psilocybin
and cancer patients. And I'm not sure if
this is necessarily an apppropo
thing to bring up with this specific
topic. And I was unable to participate
in that study because I live in New
Mexico. But I think in my opinion it's
really really critical that we get as
you know as much you know mental
whatever the word is calming and help as
we can through this whole process
because it's really not a lot of fun. So
that's all. Thank you. I appreciate you
guys.
>> Don I I have a little bit of multiple
roles here. I'm also a researcher at UNM
and I I I'm gonna share with you that we
actually have it probably may well be
the same study. It's called Rekindle and
um it's predominantly for people with
with cancer and have had issues
adjusting with mood mood or anxiety um
uh changes. It's actually using a
injectable psychedelic. It's not
psilocybin, but it basically is from the
point of view that it breaks into
psilocin bloodstream. Um and so that's
here in Albuquerque. So, if that's
something of interest to you, um you can
if uh you could the study is called
Rekindle. Um uh and if you if you uh
Googled Rekindle New Mexico, you should
get access to that.
I'd like to like maybe throw open a
little bit to discussion. Any any other
people have comments on you Don's issue
and that we talked some about about the
timing of um of eligibility?
>> If not, you know, we we can move on to
other questions. Um I still have an open
question out there for um other
inservices that people would like to to
see through this committee.
And just as a reminder for everyone, if
you're interested in speaking, all you
need to do is go ahead and raise your
hand. In order to do so, um within the
system, within the team system, there's
just a if you're on a computer, there is
a little hand icon that says raise
underneath it uh about in the middle of
the screen at the very top. And [snorts]
if you're on the app on the phone, if
you click on the three ellipses in the
menu and then the hand icon will appear
and you can select it. If you are
joining through voice only on a
telephone, if you press star five, that
will raise your hand.
And then once that occurs, we'll call on
you. And then uh to unmute once your
name has been called on a computer, the
uh unmute is the microphone icon and it
is on the upper right area of the team's
window. And if it's on a phone, it's
usually in the lower left of the team's
app. However, please be aware some
different models of phone may have the
muter uh unmute icon in a different
location. If you are on a telephone for
voice only, please press star six to
unmute yourself.
>> All right. Thank you, Dominic. And on
that note, we have James Brown. James,
I've enabled your microphone. Can you go
ahead and unmute yourself and begin when
you're ready, please?
>> Hello everyone and Dr. Leeman. Again,
thank you for putting this committee on.
Um my thoughts on this sir are
you know if we really can focus back on
that ICD bin code of the Z51.5
you know that was approved in the other
committee um you know sometimes early on
is very important on this Larry you know
that and as a serotonin
you know based receptor that we're
looking at here you know that's
intestinal a lot of our serotonin is
about 80% is intestinal besides in the
brain And with that, you know, release
that we get um for certain cancers, this
is very important that we treat it early
on versus late. Um so early versus
latent is going to be important, you
know, in those phases and looking at the
ICD10 coding and how can we
do that? I don't know if that needs to
be a separate topic, Larry, but I think
this is a great topic to get into um for
people because as we treat different
diseases,
um this modality is going to be used
differently for each one and we can
establish those um
I guess that needed curriculum or that
needed [snorts] protocols as we get to
that protocol phase and we can look at
that. But I think it's important to look
at early versus, you know, late because
sometimes,
you know, ceremonial is going to be
important here. And I wanted to also
bring that in. Um, we've had kind of
discussed that the last time. Um, I'm
not sure if that's, you know, part of
one of the other topics that's in there
with ceremonial versus traditional in
the essence of,
um, you know, of this use for the end of
life therapy or cancer or whatever comes
in there. So that's my thoughts. Larry
just to start.
>> Thank you
>> James. This is Larry. Um you know thank
you very much. I think the ceremony
would uh might come into the uh plan of
care that would be so I think it is
covered by what we have there. And um I
I appreciate you know you're you're
bringing up the early light. Okay. I
think that um and Chris Cwell, who's
going to be presenting a little bit
later in this meeting, you know, when I
talked to her a day or two ago, brought
up, you know, there's going to be people
that may benefit at multiple times.
There may be people who are may benefit
from the time of diagnosis, um where
they're dealing with, you know, dealing
with the vet and then if there is
progression later on, um you closer to
end of life may. So, it may it may be a
the answer to the question might be both
times.
Is Christine Caldwell on the call right
now?
>> I do not see them in the uh in the list
of attendees. Larry
Okay. Well, I'll [clears throat]
as we're discussing, I'm going to try to
reach out to uh reach out to them. I I
sent her the link yesterday. She I I
estimated that probably um we would have
some preliminary discussion and that she
would probably start at 3:30, but um
certainly if we don't have more more
questions, we might. Um, I'm going to
extract one more question out of James's
James's uh what he talked about because
James I I think you started talking
about coding and um I think you you were
starting to really address another area
that you know that is going to be how is
how is this paid for? How is how is what
is going to be the funding mechanisms?
What is going to be billable is and what
is not going to be um uh you know
billable. Um, I know we have had
discussions at the last meeting about
the potential for the end of life care
to potentially include the uh a partner,
a caregiver. Um, I think that may be
another thing that may be difficult to
get uh get covered. Um, there may be
areas like that that are potentially
coverable uh by the by the equity fund.
So, those are just some some thoughts
for mine on um on on the coding and all,
but I'd be c very interested in other
people talking about that issue.
>> James, your microphone credentials are
still enabled. You may unmute whenever
you're ready.
>> Uh thank you, sir. Hey, Larry and
everybody. um you know if we go back in
New Mexico we need to look at what's the
most commonly built
you know coding around this you know
through the Medicaid and Medicare pull
that data if we can and see if we can
say you know with that Z51.5
was is it is it something that I think
it's going to matter and if we could
also get the
the state versus the demographics within
the state itself if we could get are a
lot of these codings happening in Santa
Fe, New Mexico or are they happening in
the rural community as well
because that's also something Larry to
look at and to address is make sure we
um
probably this is going to apply across
the board to everybody you know in the
state. So I just want to make sure we're
capturing all that if we could get that
data I think it'd be important.
Thank you, James. I'm I'm actually
trying to contact our speaker here and
see if uh there's been a technical
problem or see where we're at.
>> Next, I'm requesting to speak. I'm
sorry.
>> I'm so sorry. Go ahead.
I have a text from her saying that uh
registered twice and never received a
confirmation or link to join. Um if I
give her phone number, uh is someone
here able to text her a link to come on
now? How do you think we should handle
this?
>> Yeah, Larry, if you can uh go ahead and
uh send that on over to Johnny and I and
email. That way we're not putting phone
numbers in chat or anything. Um,
>> and then Johnny, if you could please
reach out to her, I'd appreciate it.
>> Well, we'll do.
>> Next up, requesting to speak is Denali.
Denali, I've enabled your microphone
credentials. You may unmute yourself
whenever you're ready.
>> Hi, committee. Um and chair Leman
grateful for the opportunity to address
the board on this issue of uh
affordability and how we're going to
cover care. I think um perhaps this gets
the question of the equity fund and
whether that might cover um a a
caregiver or a loved one who otherwise
would not be um be eligible for for
coverage. Something really important for
us to think about when we're thinking
about the equity fund is right that um
we definitely want things like the
Medicaid population that that be um a
term of eligibility, but that's just the
baseline. There are going to be so many
other populations who want to be able to
access the equity fund. And I think that
this example of um auxiliary
um natural supports to the person who's
directly receiving care is is a really
great example of of the need for for a
more expansive definition within the
equity fund for eligibility.
>> Thank you.
Johnny, you should have received an
email um with the phone number for
Christine.
>> I don't see anything yet, but I will
keep an eye out for a minute.
While we wait on that, next up
requesting to speak is Trina Zer. Trina,
I've enabled your microphone
credentials. You may unmute yourself
whenever you're ready.
>> Hi, Larry and everyone. Uh, this
question is maybe something that bleeds
into another committee. Um, and I I
don't recall if we've talked about it
yet, but my question is about how a
person who perhaps has
a terminal diagnosis
um, but is being provided, they're
getting their medical care from either
an entity like the VA being federal
wouldn't be able to make a referral for
something like psilocybin
therapy. um or just a provider who
uh doesn't want to endorse such a thing
or wouldn't provide a referral to that.
I'm I'm wondering
what you envision for the structure of
this program for where someone could go
to
get that referral from a provider who
would be able to vet their medical
information and such and be able to, you
know, certify, for lack of a better
word, that they would be eligible for
this.
James, your microphone credentials have
been enabled. You can unmute yourself
whenever you're ready, sir.
>> Uh, thank you again and and Larry. Um,
when I look up some of the data, I
remember, you know, with my time with
the the lung association, uh, lung
disease is the giant is the one of the
most common and, uh, I know it's one of
the highest numbers for lung cancers is
definitely up there for New Mexicans
dying and and treatment of in our
hospices. I know we see a lot of lung
cancer. We see a lot of diabetes.
um those are definitely health
conditions that are the tops that I see
besides hypertension which again as we
discuss health conditions later that'll
be important um but if we go back and
pull those other types of cancers um I
think it'll be important as a group to
go back and see you know definitely some
of these qualify already if they have
COPD asthma emphyma things that are very
chronic lung type of conditions um those
people can definitely get treatment in
different ways than some of these other
maybe intestinal um or specific um
organ, you know, you could say diseases
um you know, [snorts] and again, we want
to stage those out. So, if we do pick a
disease state, let's say stage one
through four commonly, you know, and
look at the just the guidelines too for
um cancers so that make sure we're all
talking the same national cancer stuff.
And if that matters at all, I'm not sure
if it does. Um, but when I look up some
of that data, that was just my thoughts
on at least initially, um,
you know, as we start breaking down, you
know, what we're doing. That's all.
Over.
>> Thank you, James.
Okay. And uh we're working right now
with regard to uh getting uh the
information that we need to for our
guest speaker so that we can see about
getting that done. Uh and I see that
Larry is working on that uh at the
moment. So um
uh is there anyone else who would like
to speak on the topic the topics raised
so far? Then I'll go back. Here's the
the seven topics that were brought up in
the last uh the last meeting.
Uh established definition and scope for
end of life criteria, therapeutic team
development, inclusion of family and
caregivers, sites of end of life care,
education and workforce development,
development of psilocybin assisted
therapy, end of life care plans, and
ongoing review and updates.
So, we're making the connection with
Christine Caldwell. Um, and then she'll
be able to come on. I'm going to start
doing an introduction to Chris with the
hopes that uh she's on by the time my
introduction uh introduction ends. Um uh
you know Chris is was a former professor
at Nuropa a therapist focused on uh on
sematic work. Um she's a leader
nationally in um you know end of life
psychedelic care actually has a you know
a course that's that's well known that's
uh that's available. um she's been a you
know consultant with other studies and I
think she's you know a very valuable
person to be sharing um information and
as I mentioned I I think at this at this
session she was going to I believe focus
on you know the care team and the and
the plan of care um but I'd imagine that
that Chris may be a good person for us
in general to um uh to speak to she um I
mentioned her up in Colorado she
actually lives in Oregon now so she's
had ties to both Colorado and Oregon
which are um you know both of the other
states. So I think she's
well has information on both of those
states and in my conversation with her
has lots of very practical information
about things like dosing and redossing
and and uh um and such.
Johnny, have you been successful in
sending um her a link?
>> Not yet.
Larry, in the meantime, since we have a
moment, maybe uh this would be a good
time to set the date for the next
meeting.
>> Excellent. An idea
>> so that we're uh Yeah. Um the one thing
we have requested and this is just so
everybody is aware is um uh and I think
most people know that our priority at
the moment because of the timeline of
how long it takes to cultivate uh the
medicine um is that our our primary goal
at the moment is to get those
regulations completed. And so with that
in mind, um what we would like is uh to
actually hold off on some of the other
committees just until after session. Um
and the main reason is so that we can
focus on the um the cultivation and
testing aspects while uh session is
going on because quite a few people
including many of you who are here as
attendees to this meeting get pulled
into the roundhouse or into other
legislative duties or support. And so we
do recommend or we are requesting that
that happens at um uh after the session.
So, uh, with that in mind, Larry, is
there a particular date that would work
better for you?
>> Yeah. Okay. So, so Dom, so we're
basically talking about like in the
first not not before the first week in
February, if I have it correct.
>> When does session end?
>> Session actually ends on um February uh
19th. So, we'd really be looking at
anytime after the 19th of February.
That's a Thursday. So, if you did want
to keep um the same time frame, I would
recommend uh Thursday, February 26th.
So, it would put it at just about a
month.
>> Yeah, it's um fortunately not a good day
for me. And
um and you said the last day is the
19th.
>> Yes, the last day of session is the
>> Okay. Now, would you would that day not
be a good day at the last day?
Yeah, there there's too many things and
items that happen on that day quite
frankly we would not be able to
guarantee support for meeting at that
time.
>> Okay,
>> on that day but any anytime after that
so that could include Friday the 20th uh
or beyond that.
>> Okay.
Um, how did So, I'd like to propose
Friday the 20th um from 1 to 3 PM.
>> Okay, that time is open currently. So,
uh, unless there's any objections. If
somebody has an objection, raise your
hand, please. How does that sound,
Larry? [laughter]
>> Sounds good to me.
Okay. So, we will get that scheduled for
Friday the 20th um at from 1 to 3. So,
thank you.
See, we will always figure it. Now, uh
Larry, there is in the chat there was a
request uh to summarize some of the
topics for people who could not attend.
Um, and I'll put that uh the uh that
that slide back up on the screen uh if
you would like. if you would like to go
ahead and summarize that.
Here we go. Oh, and
I just finished talking to Chris
Caldwell. She just got the link and
should be coming on uh quickly.
Apologies for I've been sort of trying
to do that at the same time as chair of
the meeting here. But if I believe I
heard it correctly, there's an interest
in summarizing the topics and the scopes
and responsibilities.
>> Yes, that is correct, Larry. And I've
got that slide up. Uh the those seven
points that were created and they were
put in the chat earlier in the meeting.
>> Okay. Um I I'll be happy to to give my
my perspective and my my recall on this
and uh um as I say hopefully Chris will
be arriving at the meeting soon. So for
the you know the the definition scope
that's really some of the discussion we
had here and the the sentiments of the
committee were um that this is not like
a focused on the very end of life in
hospice but that we were supportive of a
a relatively broad spectrum um which
would could be from the time of
diagnosis. Um it also could you know
involve people that are reaching the
natural end of uh their life through
through aging. So that was that was
really all the sentiment. There wasn't
anyone who was not in favor of that part
of it there. The therapeutic team
development. Um we talked about the
advantages of a of a of a team and uh
the team could potentially include you
know a facilitator level of a um that
would be someone who would be sitting
with the person could can have a
potentially a therapist that has you
know um uh is a licensed therapist could
all potentially be part of the team.
there's a sentiment that we really want
to um we want to make sure that to keep
this affordable that if we can try to
use that type of a team that would be
helpful. And we had a discussion that um
this may require the uh the board to
establish a role for a facilitator uh
that could potentially be a licensed
role. there is discussion that that is
within the scope of the board and do and
would not need to go back to the
legislature to do that.
um inclusion of family and caregivers
and we touched briefly on that that the
idea is that that this is different in a
lot of ways end of life than um uh than
depression, PTSD and substance use and
that end of life is is indicated that um
can potentially include caregivers and
partners and and that that would be a
potential. We [snorts] have started to
have some of the discussion on how would
that be how would that look and you know
the idea of coding that and um uh Denali
had talked at one point about that this
may be an appropriate use of the
potentially the equity fund to to cover
that uh sites of end of life care. Um
the idea was to have a wide range but
that that there was a sentiment
throughout that that often at home is
the best place for end of life care and
to work on a way of um a way of making
that making that available.
Um educational workforce development is
kind of associated some with the um you
know the therapeutic team uh therapeutic
team development. Um there's also some
conversation and I think Chris coming on
the call is helpful that there are
actually places that people can get you
know more um more focused uh focused
training on on end of life and that you
know the idea that hopefully everybody
who's um you know familiar and offering
um psilocybin therapy um would have
experience with end of life but there
may be people that that's more of a a
focus you know the the terms being used
now are things like psychedelic doulas,
psychedelic chaplain.
Um
the um development of the of the end of
life care plan, you know, we we haven't
had that much of discussion of that yet,
but you know, the idea is that that
would look at different models like, you
know, one treatment, multiple multiple
treatments, ways to support that. And
then the ongoing review and updates is
simply the um you know having the idea
that that we would both get this
committee and the public information
about the studies that have happened so
far. What have been the experiences for
instance um uh there's a fairly vigorous
experience in uh um in Canada with
rooster thrive of um of using
psilocybin. So sharing that. So that
would be my relatively brief summary of
each of the um each of the issues.
I'm sure I'm missing out important
things in there. So, please if people
want to add in there, raise their hand.
And uh again, uh checking, have we Chris
Caldwell, come on.
>> Yes, Larry, I do believe they are. And
Chris, I have made you as a presenter.
Um you just need to unmute yourself if
you're not familiar on the phone. It's a
star six to unmute. But it looks like
you've already done that.
>> I'm here. Yeah, I'm I'm I I am so sorry.
I you know, you had just resent me that
registration link, but I tried that
several times and never got a a link to
join. So, I'm bummed. Um
>> well, Chris, we're all you haven't
missed anything. We're all here waiting
for you. So, um we really appreciate you
you're still being here and I've talked
you up a few times during the meeting.
So people's anticipation is probably
good.
>> Oh, great. Yeah. Just like just like
being told that this is the best movie
you've ever seen and then you go, "What?
What was that?"
Anyway, what So, um, so do you want me
to launch into what you and I chatted
about the other day?
>> Larry, you're muted.
>> Chris, I think that would be great. We
have spacious time here. So I think that
you could focus on those issues, take
some questions, kind of see where where
it goes. But um you know, we've talked
about in general uh we have two hours
trying to have these meetings be about
an hour and a half. So you know, you
could easily take you know, up to 30
minutes and present and that would leave
us adequate time I think for discussion.
Well, I think what I'd like to do um is
you know, we talked about sort of two of
your two and a half of your six
principles and you know that was like
the therapeutic team and I would say
flashwork development and then the other
piece of that was you know the the plan
of care and I'll I'll start with you
know talking about the the therapeutic
team um but I would like if somebody has
a question or a comment if you if
somebody could just flag it and and I'll
stop. Um but I I first of all I so
appreciate this opportunity and I again
I'm so bummed. Um I guess for for folks
that don't know me. So Chris Caldwell,
founder, executive director of end of
life psychedelic care. I'm just going to
say we we organize our nonprofit around
four pillars. So education first and
foremost. I do as much as I can free
online events. uh we've uh had like some
6,000 people register for our events
since uh we started in 2023. We have
professional courses. So I spend a lot
of time thinking about the kinds of
things that you guys are now um
discussing and wrestling with. You know,
how do we best serve people toward the
end of life? Um the other thing we do is
we connect people together either the
professionals with each other, the
consumers, clients with each other or
then with with each other. um uh clients
with uh people both um experiencing end
of life and psychedelic care. Um I also
wanted to mention because I think it's
germanine even though if it's not gerine
from a psychedelic standpoint. So um I'm
just tickled to have received a um a
grant through healing hearts changing
minds in collaboration with uh legar the
Christian psychedelic society and um uh
the institute for rural psychedelic
care. We're going to be running a pilot
across three sites, uh, Northern
California, Chicago, and Atlanta,
pairing a pali of care physician with an
end of life doula or a chaplain. So,
we're all about demonstrating the
efficacy in this case of ketamine to
reduce existential, psychological,
uh, even physical pain of distress. um
and with a spiritual model um uh
integrated into this. So when I think
about what's applicable for uh New
Mexico going forward, I think what we're
going to be doing um in building this
protocol even though it's using ketamine
could be applicable.
Okay. So having said all that and thank
you um I I'll start with this idea of of
um your principal therapeutic team and I
want to start out by saying you know
when we think about this and I'm sure
you guys have already talked about this.
So you know it's not necessarily a
psychotherrapeutic
intervention. Uh it could be
psychological it could be ontological. I
like to think of it as either a
psychosspiritual or a psychobiospiritual
type of intervention, if that's even the
right word. Um because now we're getting
closer to you know as you talk um as
hospice uh talks about total pain. So
we're really looking at you know the
ability of something like a psilocybin
to be not just transdiagnostic
but also to help an individual through
many many different types of conditions.
And in this case, yes, um what they're
faced with psychologically, physically,
existentially, spiritually, um as
they're faced at this time of life. And
so, so that's kind of number one for me
um as I think about this. And then um
you know this the second thing is um is
we always talk about um or I I think of
it as a continuum. So you know we talk
about clients who are recently diagnosed
all the way to being really close to the
end of life. So of course um as you have
been talking about expanding that
definition of end of life well then your
plan of care, your therapeutic team,
your training requirements will all
differ. Um, and that's all to the good
because my my hope is that of course is
you really don't turn anybody away
unless there's a really um definite sort
of physical or or um uh psychological
reason. So, but it will it will be very
different obviously uh depending on
where that person is on that continuum.
Um si similarly you know if we're
talking about in um an in clinic or inh
hospital um uh session and facilitation
and integration preparation that's
different than inh home um obviously um
and so I'll come back to that that one a
little bit when we talk about um plan of
care
but you know basically when I when I
think about this too another another key
factor here is that uh psilocybin
therapy is different when you're working
with people faced with a
life-threatening or serious illness. So,
you know, and what I what I do is, you
know, I don't replicate when I think
about my educational programming, I
don't replicate anything that's already
being done out there. There's plenty of
really wonderful um psychedeling
organizations. So I come along and I
augment um and as we have begun to get
all this information and I also
collaborated on a psychedelic death
worker study that I think some of you
might have might have um participated
in. We've been able to gather a lot of
information um and to me it's along two
main uh dimensions. One is what is that
client's mindset when they've been told
that they have a terminal or
life-threatening or chronic um illness.
And what are those practices that are
then different, you know, that um you as
facilitators, uh prescribers, clinicians
need to know about um in order to to
serve this this very very different kind
of a mindset individual.
So, if I could share um that with you
first sort of as a base level here and
then I and then I'll have one more
comment and then I would love to kind of
break and and and hear um hear your
questions or even better comments. So if
we think about a client's mindset after
they've been told that they have a
terminal illness or they have cancer and
this is true even if people are given
like two years to live or or they're
given they're told that their death is
fairly imminent um that they they go
through through these different states.
So you know first and foremost a
physiological state change. So, not only
are they faced with their ongoing
disease process and the pain, their
treatment side effects um uh the
physical fragility um that can um
influence their emotional, their
cognitive and their spiritual capacity.
U of course what's going on
psychologically, they have that fear of
dying, that anxiety, that depression.
And I want to I want to say too, um uh
some of you have listened to the
conversation I had with Thomas Hardle.
He was the first Canadian approved for
psilocybin therapy to Health Canada. He
had the benefit of seven psilocybin
journeys through the the remaining time
of his life which was from 2020 to 2024.
And he started with I want to reduce the
debilitating anxiety that prevents me
from being with my family in the way I I
want to be. He started with that as his
as his intention. He came back three
months later because the anxiety started
to return. But then he moved into a more
existential consciousness and became
basically a pans psychic pany whatever
it is where everything is consciousness
where his cancer was consciousness. So
if we have an ability to help people
through these various sort of states of
mind that there are now existing in and
help them it is so wonderful and so it's
not just necessarily a one on one and
done. It's like let's look at the total
scale of of what we are as humans and
and if you happen to believe that we are
we are all consciousness to me all the
better. So in any case, from a
psychological landscape, folks are now
faced with guilt. They're faced with
shame. They're faced with unresolved
inner conflicts.
Third, there is existential distress.
What is the meaning? Why am I here? I'm
worthless. Um they don't really have a
will to live sometimes. Uh sometimes if
they were the matriarch or the
patriarch, it's like I've lost I've lost
my reason to be here. Um and then there
are um socioultural realities big there
of course are family dynamics. Um what
what is the family dynamic? What are
those relationships? Are they
supportive? Are they obstructive? Are
they chaotic? And then sort of a a
relation to that is you know that there
could be caregiver fatigue. Um, you
know, I'm I'm sure all of you that work
in this space know um the spouse who
just wants to take care of their their
their spouse who's ailing. They get
sicker themselves actually. And so now
you've got an individual who's dealing
with guilt because of their spouse
burning out trying to take care of them.
Then in terms of socioultural you also
have are there strong cultural or or
strong social supports or is this person
living in isolation?
Then as another dimension you've got
what is their spirituality? What are
their spiritual beliefs? What do they
believe about death? What do they
believe about atonement? Do they think
they're going to go to hell? So so much
is going through this person's mind. So
what does that mean for us when we want
to take care of these people?
Um goes right into clearly a greater
need for collaboration.
You know more often than not we're going
to require um a medical clearance and of
course as that person gets sicker that
person gets more physically frail that
becomes more and more important. Um,
we're going to look at dosing
considerations as their body may become
more physically frail. Um, we may want
to coordinate with paliative care teams
and depending what your specific role is
as the facilitator um, not just with
physicians but with therapists, with
chap, grief counselors, with doulas. Um,
then we look at meeting that person
where they are spiritually. So,
integrating spiritual frameworks into
this whole process right from the get-go
and being able to assess where this
individual is at and how you can honor
that client's spiritual beliefs and
needs. Um, uh, third, working with
families. You know, I think this
training should require a whole session
on what it means to work within a family
dynamic because it's just so important.
all the way from just basic education
needing to be a part and I know you have
talked about including the family in
terms of participating in their own
journeys or maybe participating in group
journeys with the client but you know
obviously that's a very um personal
decision between the client and um the
family and there's plenty of reasons why
it's not necessarily a good thing but
nonetheless they need to be part of this
whole process Maybe they're just brought
in for the preparation in the
integration, but they need to to be a
participant. And by the way, what do you
as a facilitator do if you've got one uh
adult child saying, "No way. I ain't
letting my mother go, you know, go on a
psychedelic trip." What are we as a
facilitator going to do? Are we going to
honor the client's wish or are we going
to honor the daughter's wish because
maybe she's going to sue you?
um informed consent takes on a much
expanded
um sort of definition and role here. You
may have to talk to your client about
yeah you know what you could die you
could die during this journey or you
could die shortly thereafter we have to
talk about expanded consent maybe
there's a healthc care surrogate that
needs to be a part of this so a lot of
transparency regarding risks
um and another big part of this is
assessing cognitive capacity and
decision making ability. So again, more
training, more understanding of what
informed consent must look like. And
then, you know, another aspect of
consideration for um facilitators and
for training is what does preparation
and integration look like? And I'll come
back to that, but very important. You
know, Larry and I talked about this a
little bit. It's like could be longer,
could be shorter. um both on the
preparation side and and on the
integration side. I certainly have heard
a lot of stories about individuals who
are very very were very very close to
end of life and their integration was
pretty much wow that was great. No, that
that's not what it was. It was it was
more like I am at peace now. I am now
grateful for my life. I now realize that
there is no pain upon separating from my
my physical world into this other world
that I'm I'm going to. So there's a lot
of considerations there in terms of
building that container, understanding
that again their needs, their mindset,
their inner world, their intentions are
very very different. And then we look at
energetic hygiene and I I generally
speak in terms of this uh for you as the
facilitator. What does that really mean?
I mean it's important you know for all
of us who've gone through psychedelic
facilitator training. It's important to
learn about energetic hygiene for
yourself. But when you're talking about
working with somebody who's closer to
the end of life, there can be um
energetic sharing that's beyond what you
would normally get. You you've got a
spiritual discharge potential, a lot of
energy discharge from an individual
looking at the end of life for whatever
reason. You might have entities come and
visit you during a journey um coming to
support your client. So what is it that
you need to learn about energetic
hygiene and taking care of your yourself
and preparing um before during the
journey and after. Um another thing that
has come up when we did our psychedelic
death worker study and in talking to a
lot of people who've been doing this
specific work for decades is the
complimentary sort of integrative
practices that go along with it. I don't
know if
if working with people with a terminal
illness just lends itself more to this,
but it certainly seems in talking to
people um that are experienced that they
bring in Reiki, they bring in
meditation, they bring in guided
visualizations or some gentle gentle
massage or yoga. Um, and in many cases
you can get to a point where you say,
"Hm, you know what? We're not here to to
administer psilocybin. We're we're here
to help you gain peace with your death
and dying. So, you know what?
Psychedelics might not be a really great
thing for you right in this moment.
We're just going to sit here and do a
guided visualization." So always need to
have that in lie of a psychedelic to
have those integrative practices andor
they're important during the preparation
phase andor in the integration phase.
One of the other things we always want
to talk about because it always comes up
is made
related clarification. So, um I will say
when we do our trainings, we we never
say yes, we're going to give you some
psilocybin followed by your your your
other medications. Um but it's more a
matter of saying all right and I I have
heard stories both ways where they have
used psilocybin or ketamine and said hm
I and I already had let's say they
already had maid approved
then they decided that they
weren't going to use their maid they
were okay there's this gentleman that um
I I he was on a panel I just moderated
um lived lives uh has been living with
quadriplegia for some 31 years and was
ready to die because he was he was fine
but then um the pain the pain became
excruciating something happened and I'm
sorry medically I don't I don't really
know what it was but he wanted to die
decided he was going to use a psilocybin
in a um a church ceremony psilocybin
church ceremony
and literally
fell in love, got a new lease in life
life. He literally fell in love, met a
woman and fell in love. And so now he
has no interest in dying. But then
conversely, there's stories where an
individual has taken ketamine or
psilocybin and said, "Yes,
this is what I am going to do." And they
get peace or clarity around using the um
the the maid. Um the other thing that um
I you know I I don't know what's going
to happen in New Mexico um uh and so I'm
really curious about this but um there's
certainly a lot of potential for lowd
dose work with psilocybin and ketamine
for that matter. Um, I mean, I
personally love the idea of of um
psilocybin micro doing support groups,
whether that's for an individual with a
terminal illness or cancer diagnosis or
a grief support group. Um, that would
come together. And I'm not sure where
New Mexico is is with that. Um but in
any case then kind of bringing that back
to this this idea of what a therapeutic
team should look like can look like and
what kind of the development or training
should look like. You know, I guess I go
back to pragmatic and this is where I
really want to ask you guys because I I
I don't know, but given what I
understand your current law is that um
the um the psilocybin administration is
via a clinician, so a medical or mental
health clinician. And I know that's it's
it's more broad than that in that I
think one of the things um you are all
working on is trying to broaden who in
fact may administer or maybe be as part
of the team. But I'm thinking in the in
the very near term since I'm assuming
that um that you're going to be able to
start dosing sessions
uh in um 2027, early 2027,
then looking at the therapeutic team
that has been sanctioned by um uh SB219
would mean it's a clinician that would
need both psyched psychedelic training
if they don't have that and then I would
argue um
specific end of life related training in
addition to that ideally then you know
there would be individuals who maybe
aren't able to administer and this could
be end of life doulas chaplain um
um well I suppose that because I guess
hospice social workers hospice hospice
nurses they would fit under the the
clinician um role or definition. But in
any case, to then to be able to train
individuals who understand what it means
to work with somebody um who's dying and
actually has sat through transitions,
which is just amazing, and then be there
as part of a um a therapeutic care team
would be great. So, you know, um I think
also um
when when I think about the therapeutic
care team and you've got your
prescribers and I'm not sure if your
prescribers are necessarily then going
to also be the the practitioners or the
facilitators. But in any case, I think
there needs to be training for the
medical screening say in addition to um
training um for the those that will be
doing the facilitation because I I'll
say that the training that I normally do
is for the facilitator. I do one
ketamine training that is specific for
the prescriber. So the physician or the
nurse practitioner. So again, there's
obviously there's overlap, but there's
also some distinct areas um of training
that a facilitator wouldn't necessarily
have to do. So I I I hope I'm not
rambling um too much. Um but I guess you
know, one other thing I Yeah, I'm sorry.
I'll stop there.
>> Oh, no, no, no. Chris, I just wanted to
let you know that we do have uh somebody
who has a question. Um we have uh James
Brown who's got his hand up. James,
>> uh, you are enabled. Go ahead.
>> There we go. Thank you. Can you guys
hear me?
>> Yes, sir.
>> Yes,
>> Katherine. Thank you so much. Um, I just
had a one or two questions for you.
Amazing. Um, I really appreciate your
knowledge and info. Uh, first and
foremost, u, my questions were around
the facilitator and with those uh,
administration sessions. Were you guys
doing a nondirective approach or were
they using a
a semi directive non-directive and then
did you guys have them I'm sure there
was some type of client release form
there in that specific plan that they
were using per person. Can you explain
that a little bit more and go into that
detail?
Let let me take the first one um the
first question and then you might need
to repeat the the the second part of
that. Um in terms of nondirective you
know that is such a great question. um
in in the states of Oregon and Colorado
uh as a non-medical model it is purely
we we purely teach a nondirective
approach
and um
um I'm hesitating because there there
are to me there's times when um there
should be interventions
and you really again need to meet the
client where they are um I like client
informed therapeutic approach sometimes
now but I also will say um you know if
we're talking about the preparation the
se dosing session and the integration
the dosing session primarily is
nondirective
but it's but when you start to see a
client become agitated
um and you feel you need to intervene
Um then yes there there there there are
ways that are that are more
nondirective. There are there are things
that maybe are more um uh interdirective
just a little bit different. Um I don't
know that I'm answering your question. I
I just I hesitate because I never like
to say it's all this and it's not
something else because depending on on
where your client is, if your client
believes they're really dying in the
moment, you're going to intervene. Um,
and sometimes just saying, um, no,
you're not going to die is is not going
to cut it. So, there's need there's
times for interventions that I think are
are really important.
Um, but generally speaking, you're
inviting that person to have their own
journey.
But then I can tell you other times and
I love to tell this story again.
Colorado, Oregon, nondirective model,
but um I don't know if any of you know
Hunt Priest with Lagari. He was one of
the clergy members that participated in
the John's Hopkins research back in um
was it 2019? 200 whenever I think it was
2019.
And um Hunt tells this story himself
where he felt an electrical pulse in his
thigh
and um he was getting I'm I don't want
to put words in his mouth necessarily,
but I'm going to say he was like getting
agitated and the facilitator literally
put his or her hand on his throat chakra
and released that energy and Hunt
describes it as a condundalini
experience and it freed him and it
really was an epiphany moment for him.
Now, that was a very, very well-trained
facilitator that did that. But I
absolutely love that story because
nondirective may not just always be the
answer. So, that was a a long a long way
of answering your question, James.
>> Oh, it completely did, Katherine. And
I'm a big believer of in especially end
of life therapy that sometimes you need
to use a redirective
and you know and [clears throat] that
sometimes would be like we've been
taught like I've been taught before with
the hands, feets and head you know that
you can do certain touching that's been
agreed upon preession and that you know
that preparatory work like you've been
saying is very important the state and
some of those expectations are set so
that person um and I'm glad that you've
uh answered that. Thank you so much.
That was my my question on that.
>> What was the second one?
>> In your settings that you guys did um
and were practicing those journeys and
experiences and healing, did you guys
were those in more of a the setting? Was
that a uh a building? Was that somewhere
that you guys did in a retreat setting?
Was that something that was only
indoors, per se?
>> Um, well, okay. So, you know, I gather
stories from hundreds of people. So, I'm
I'm not I don't necessarily look at just
one what we did this one oneoff time
here or there. So, um, and I, you know,
my educational programs are for anybody
whether they work underground or or not
or with whatever medicine that they use.
So, it it runs the gamut. There's been
in in clinic well let me put it this way
um in licensed service centers in
Oregon. Um then there's um a retreat.
There's uh the survivorship collective
which was um a nonprofit which was
founded to organize groups psilocybin
retreats in Oregon um and Colorado
wherever their state legal or or like in
the Netherlands for example they have
they had the benefit of being on a
property where they could actually go
outside at least after the journey. So
there was a sort of blend of indoor
outdoor of course underground I know
people who do it in any number of places
including uh outdoor generally speaking
in the individual's home that's where
most people like to have psilocybin
delivered is in their home. Um, and then
this the um the pilot that I talked
about that we've gotten funding for that
will be an inhome tetamine therapy
administered um intramuscular um I am.
So um there's that. I I and and I I will
just say I'm a big fan of goof models
which is why I'm going to be really
interested in Larry's work. Um the the
the retreat that was developed in
Portland, Oregon is amazing. I mean they
do four four prep sessions. They come
together for I think it's two psilocybin
sessions over a five or five day period
of time and then they've got at least
four integration sessions. You know what
we see with people and the these
retreats are um designed specifically
for people with cancer. What we see with
those kind of group models is a real
bonding that enhances, deepens, extends
the therapeutic benefit. No question in
my mind. Um I'm a big Roots to Thrive uh
fan uh who developed the the group model
in in Canada when Health Canada first
brought that psilocybin therapy forward.
I also want to mention when you talk
about touch, you know, because it's
something obviously that you guys will
talk about as well in terms of training
and what will the state of New Mexico
allow. So, you know, in in Oregon, you
actually you do the the the shoulder,
the feet, the hands, and hugs.
In Colorado, you do the the feet, the
hands, the shoulder, no hugs. Um, I
also, um, um, owned and operated a a
pretty significantly sized home
healthcare agency back in Florida. And
so I really understand helping
individuals who are aging in place. Um
and you know in terms of touch, one of
the things our home healthcare aids
always did um not they they always
offered but pending of course the um the
condition of the skin rubbing lotion or
oils on the forins for on the shins on
the forearms. I almost said for skins
that would not have been good. Uh, okay.
So, on the forearms and on the shins,
you know, rubbing oil or lotion and it's
just so so soothing for an individual.
So, anyway, that's a whole whole other
issue.
>> Catherine, thank you again so much for
that. I mean, that's what I was um
asking about and you answered it
completely. Um, with my experience, I
think it's important that this committee
and this advisory board look at options
for people at end of life and the
various different settings for the
various different ICD10 coding that
we're doing and and you know potentially
in my experiences allow for certain
safety of course um but allow certain
things to occur you know as long as it's
agreed upon up first in those plans. Um
thank you so much.
>> Yeah.
So, what do you think, Larry? Should I
keep going?
>> Chris, I had a question. Um, you and I
talked some about, you know, dosing with
um, you know, dosing with folks who are
um, with more advanced cancer and
others. Do you want to share some of
that with the group?
>> Yeah. So um you know this kind of goes
back to what are the protocols then in
the cure plan going to be for um working
with somebody toward the end of life.
Again understanding that there is this
continuum
um of of like um
being newly diagnosed all the way to
very very close to the end of life. So,
you know what, one of the things we talk
about and and I have this this chart and
it's a rough dosing guide. Um, and it's
it's always, you know, you say a rough
dosing guide and you always get into
trouble. Um, um, but nobody likes to
talk about what the dosing actually
might look like. So, one of the things I
do know I want to say is that ketamine
we feel can be used all along this
continuum. And certainly some of the
stories, the story where I talked about
a gentleman um who actually used it to
decide on maid was very close to the end
of life and it was ketamine. It was
ketamine at at 7.8 milligrams per
kilogram. So it wasn't like it was some
kind of lightweight dose. Um psilocybin
um psilocybin is is really great also
throughout this continuum. You just need
to think about different dosing levels.
But there's so much that's going to go
into this f into the factor of dosing.
One of course is how psychedelically
experienced are they? Um if they're if
they're naive, so let's start with that,
you know, and let's say they're they're
still on the end where they're fairly
close to just being diagnosed, then you
know, starting with um maybe 10
milligrams, start starting with maybe 20
milligrams, um maybe starting with 10
and then going for a booster for 10. I I
you know if if it's a physically healthy
person I think a lot of times people
will will can start with 10 and go to 10
um maybe 20 and go to 10 um as a
booster.
But the other thing to keep in mind is
that as the body becomes frail then
metabolism shuts down. And I shared with
Larry a couple stories where one person
was put into the taxi cab because
nothing was happening after several
hours and their trip started in the taxi
cab. Um or maybe it was Uber. But then
the the other story where um a person
was given I think it was like 20
milligrams out the gate. Maybe it was 30
milligrams out the gate and in Oregon
the max is 50 milligrams. Nothing
happened for hours, a couple hours and
gave him another booster. Nothing
happened for hours. Um, the gentleman
got to the max 50 milligrams. Several
several hours later, all hell broke
loose. There was like vomiting and
diarrhea
for a very long period of time. So, it's
like, you know, I have a hospice
physician who's been doing this work or
I know a hospice physician doing this
work for a very long time. She'll say,
you give them a dose and you don't give
them anything more. if even if there's
no trip you know come back on a
different day maybe her philosophy is is
that person is not prepared enough so
there is that as an as an aspect of it
certainly when they're really close to
the end of life and I mean like within
um a month or weeks looking at something
like a half of a gram well excuse me
that would be 0.5 of a of 0.5 5 mill no
5 milligrams um versus 10 milligrams and
maybe another five milligram booster um
would be okay because again now this
person's this person is half on the
other side already anyway. So um and we
we believe they're already in a in a
sort of psychedelic journey without even
any psychedelics. you know, this
individual, if they're they're at a
point where they're having um deathbed
visions and they're having conversations
with their loved ones from the other
side, then arguably they don't need any
psychedelics. But then I would say a
very very low dose.
And you know, you know, Larry, the
answer to that question is always it
depends. But um I I like maybe 10, maybe
20 followed by another 10 and or Yeah.
followed by maybe another 10 short
answer.
>> And and
>> uh we have a question or uh request to
speak from Don. Don, I've enabled your
microphone credentials. Will you unmute
yourself and begin when you're ready,
please?
>> Thank you. Can everybody hear me?
>> Hello.
>> We can hear you, but very uh minimal.
>> Yeah. Hold on. I apologize ma'am. I
really appreciate your me your
information is amazing. I like you don't
have any like way to like a website or
anything that I can look into you more
way to contact you. The things you were
saying are really up my alley the
spiritual side of this and all of that.
But the question or I guess comment that
I have is if I have if somebody at what
and I'm the reason I'm kind of asking
this twice but you weren't
have connected yet. At what point do you
is it do you start to administer this
medicine if somebody has cancer? I have
stage four prostate cancer, but I'm in
treatment and the the pharmaceuticals
that I'm taking are working. So, I'm not
very thick.
I'm mentally and emotionally
thick.
So, I'm not sure how do we how do we go
about like do you know you go in and
talk to somebody and could we just take
some of this medicine just to help us
cope with all of this? You know, this a
massive amount of stuff we have to do or
do do we do you wait until I'm sicker
to start to administer this medicine or
how do what's your thoughts on all that?
Well, I I would say that um best would
be to start whenever you feel called. So
there is no need to wait.
Um
uh
yeah, there there is no need to wait.
and and earlier I was I was uh sharing
just a little bit of the story of this
Thomas Hardle who had seven psilocybin
journeys. So he had been diagnosed with
stage 4 colon cancer in 2016
and um u you know uh Canada didn't
approve this psilocybin therapy until
2020.
Um and his like I said his anxiety was
debilitating. So you know he had he was
the one that did the outreach and went
to where um you know asked asked to
apply to this new program. Um and over
the course of those seven psilocybin
journeys, he really evolved his
intention from being um a psychological
one having to do with um uh anxiety all
the way to then more existential and
spiritual questions about, you know, who
am I? What where am I going? Um, and so
I would say if if you can if you're in a
place or you can come to Oregon or
Colorado uh in a place to get with
individuals who are trained to work with
people with cancer, then I would say do
it. Do it now and then do it later. Um
and and yeah, Larry Larry said he would
give the information um about my um my
website because there is that the
conversation I had with this Thomas
Hardle is is um something that I think
everybody should listen to because he
does an extraordinarily eloquent job
describing the arc of his seven
journeys.
>> Thank you. And just for clarification
sake, uh Kate Hawk was gracious enough
to post the link to that website, Don.
So that is available in the chat. Uh
just to catch us up to speed, Asher
Weinstein in the chat asked, "Are
standard dosing metrics milligram per
kilogram?" So Chris is saying 10
milligram, kilogram, then redossing with
the same. Lawrence clarified 10
milligram synthetic equivalent, not per
kilogram. Kate Hawk commented right the
milligram per kilogram was for ketamine
and Asher's uh retort was thanks so it's
not trans mushrooms
>> well okay so Kade yeah what I said about
7 milligrams per kilogram that was for
ketamine
>> um you know and as a weight based dose
which isn't always what's needed
the the psilocybin yeah I was trying to
speak in terms of the analyte. So um 10
milligrams would be the equivalent of
one gram of dried mushrooms
approximately. Let me say approximately.
So, I I do have just a couple of more um
comments. Um but we've we've kind of
touched on a lot of these things, but in
terms of pulling it together, um and
Larry, you when you and I talked about a
sort a care plan, you know, and a care
plan obviously is very customized to
that individual. Um one one of the
things that I think a lot about and now
now as I've told you, I used to own a
home healthcare agency. So I think about
what what's what safeguards should be in
place for in the home service and I
really like the idea of a medical
screening being required and that
medical provider prescriber
determining the care plan um because
it's going to be so different for for uh
individuals there. There may, you know,
if if a um a psychotherapist is now
licensed to serve psilocybin in the
home, for example, but maybe they need a
medical person on site with them, then I
think that needs to be determined
upfront. That of course would add to the
cost. Um but generally speaking, you
know, if you start with that intake and
medical screening to determine um the
the health, relative health and
potential for any um uh drugto inter
interactions or other contraindications
that and develop that plan of care for
that individual.
I think what's really important is and I
don't know if this is going to be part
of the New Mexico model or not, but to
do assessments. When I say assessment,
sometimes they can be in the form of a
survey scale, self-administered scale
like the PHQ9 or the GAD 7. Um, in this
ketamine pilot that I'm going to be
doing in collaboration with the palative
care physicians, we are using the PHQ9,
the GAD 7, the demoralization scale 2
and the facet um the spirituality um
questions on the facet. So trying to get
at um the spirituality component of of
these individuals. But nonetheless
um this is where I think there may be a
need for more preparation sessions as
you're talking to an individual through
their psychological,
their physiological,
their existential, socioultural and
spiritual um issues. getting an
understanding of where they are at and
where it is or what it is that they want
from the psilocybin journey. Um, and in
a lot of cases, you know, you can't just
be handing these folks these survey
scales and letting them um,
self-administer them, especially when
you're really trying to understand what
are your beliefs around death and dying.
Um, are you afraid of dying? Um, um,
yeah. are you afraid you're going to
hell like I had already said. Um so
there may be a need to for uh multiple
preparation sessions. Certainly I would
also recommend that if there's an inhome
session that there's an extra inhome
safety check.
Um that will [clears throat] include a
lot of different things, not the least
of which is no guns um that aren't
locked up. So an inhome safety check
that is not just safe making it safe for
the client but it's making it safe for
the facilitator. So that's an additional
step I think that people should
consider. [clears throat]
Um and then um um I don't know Don if
that was you you alluded you alluded to
you know when you have cancer and you
have medications and treatments. So it's
like all right determining when um the
psilocybin session would be best and by
the way um uh you know I've I've read
where people undergoing chemo treatment
should wait two weeks following uh
chemotherapy to do psilocybin. On the
other hand, this same gentleman Thomas
um tells the story where he preferred um
psilocybin
uh sessions two to three days before
chemo. Um he didn't need the
anti-inflammatory meds. He felt that it
reduced or eliminated his cheo brain
effect. Uh he was able to actually help
other people because they would have the
chemotherapy in a group. um as opposed
[clears throat] to being miserable, but
he really felt it helped him go into
chemotherapy with a better attitude.
This man had 84 rounds of chemotherapy
before he died.
Um so anyway, so so there there's that
um as well. There's other, you know, the
medications, for example, um uh it's
better to uh for an individual to be on
a long-asting opioid than on a short um
lasting one. um you know because of this
psilocybin with a longer journey for
example do they hold their if they're on
uh cerakquil or something for insomnia
do they hold that dose do they not hold
that dose so a lot of of of um
considerations like that that need to be
taken into account which also could uh
uh impact dosing by the way right if a
person is on an SSRI you might want to
increase that psilocybin dose
um really a lot of attention's going to
page two is this more of an ontological
type of okay therapy I don't think
that's the right word versus
psychological but being aware that um
the psychological could turn more into
an ontological one there could be
spiritual distress there could be
spiritual emergency um that um arises as
well out of this and in preparation I
think it's really important then to be
able to um practice a lot as far as um
how can this person self-regulate? I
mean, most of us don't I mean, most of
us who are now in this space might do it
more often, but most clients, most
people do not know how to self-regulate.
And I think that needs to be practiced.
It's not just a oneandone.
Um
and then I think too a consideration
here on a care plan is um as physicians
I think many of you in this work do um
the um the physician order was it
physician orders
life sustaining treatment. So the post
plan that you would probably have to
fill out for these individuals. So
another consideration um for you and
then in an integration part of that plan
is what is that follow-on support you
know is it going to be an end of life
duel a chaplain or a family member or
another member of the community to
support this individual ongoing. So I'll
kind [laughter] of stop there again and
and um just see if there's any other
questions or comments. I'd love comments
um in terms of what you see happening in
New Mexico.
So, in the chat, uh, we have a comment
from Trina. She says, "Thank you, Chris,
for sharing your expertise with us. I
have to step away for patient care, and
I'm sorry to miss the rest of your
excellent presentation."
>> A thank you, Trina.
I believe your credentials are enabled.
Uh, Lawrence.
>> Great. Chris, thank you so much. That
that was an amazing presentation and um
I I certainly uh think it would be great
to have you back, you know, at another
time as we're moving along on our
process. Um I wanted to share both with
you and the committee that um at the
next meeting on February 20th um we're
going to have um a speaker uh from the
committee uh Jennifer KMA who's um been
in the role of psychedelic chaplain and
so we're going to have some focus on
what Chris was talking about which is
the role of spirituality spiritual
advisor so that will be on the February
and then um I'm the issues about dosing
and stuff I think um is one of the areas
that
James Brown has been uh kind enough to
offer to talk. So, I'm hoping in in
March we'll be able to set that up so
that we'll have followup to some of
these topics that that Chris has opened
up.
Anybody else have any more questions for
Chris? Uh Chris and addition to um
hearing all our thanks, we really really
do appreciate you all the wisdom you
shared with us.
I appreciate the opportunity. Um, you
know, I and as an invitation, you if you
do check out um the website, there's um
I'm doing a 90inute um presentation on
um an an overview and I go through um
the latest research. I really I've spent
a lot of time updating the presentation.
I talk about uh ketamine, psilocybin,
and MDMA. the latest research that
extends beyond when we talk about
existential or psychological distress.
And that's another thing, Larry, when
you're talking about end of life and
expanded definition. I love the work
that's being done with Parkinson's, with
MS, with ALS, um, with stroke survivors.
So, a lot of stuff going on in the
psilocybin research world that's
fascinating.
So, that's coming up in February. And
then um you know as I as I talked
upfront about this really being at least
a psychosspiritual
model um we've reformulated a lot of
what we do and as Larry knows so we're
we're doing a course
um coming up where um uh it'll be it'll
be some some some of the folks that are
really really steeped in spiritual
practices will be teaching the courses
and I'm really excited about that.
>> We do have one more uh hand raised in
the chat. Uh back to James Brown.
>> James, I've enabled your microphone.
Whenever you're ready, sir.
Just one more question for you. Sorry to
and again thank you for your time today
and answering my questions. Um
with this you you earlier you talked
about with the preparation as well as
integration uh phases.
Were those um done in a persontoerson
settings that your um experiences gather
or were they virtually? because in New
Mexico we're going to have some
challenges on with the with our
ruralness and how we can provide
services. So I just wanted to kind of
talk about that and expand on that
conversation just quickly on
>> Yeah, boy that's that's uh also a really
great question.
>> To me, ideally in person is always
better. You know, it doesn't matter if
the individual is closer to the end of
life or not faced with a terminal
illness. Um, however, like you say, if
you've got folks in rural areas, then
that may not be um, uh, available to
them. This could be though where, you
know, having a care team really comes
really can help. And, and again, I'll go
back to this idea of pairing, in my
case, it's pairing a physician with an
end of life doula, but pairing a
clinician with an endof life doula or
chaplain. um who may be able to go out
in person um and and be with this
individual to help with the preparation.
Um in in our pilot, we're going to be
having the doula do the initial intake,
then the then the physician will do the
medical screening. Um, but James, you
know, it's it's it's more important, I
think, to be able to get the help where
they are than than, you know, go, "Oh,
well, we don't have somebody that's
there locally, so we can't help you."
And certainly, um, most people now are
quite used to, um, Zoom or whatever, you
know, um, speaking uh, virtually. And so
I think that's quite fine.
It's just not as good. [laughter]
All right. Next up we have is Barack
Wolf. Barack, I've enabled your
microphone credentials. You may unmute
yourself whenever you're ready.
>> Let's see if you can hear me.
>> Yes, sir.
>> Are you here? Okay. Thank you. Well, um,
appreciate the session. Um, you know, I
think it was Trina who early on raised
an issue that I think is relevant to a
number of the comments we've had since
then, but it's never sort of been
approached directly. And that was as we
go through the, you know, the various
issues that have been raised and make
progress on them. And it's wonderful to
hear some of the in the weeds discussion
that we've had today.
um an issue arises about how will folks
you know know about this. I think the
question was if my doctor or my hospice
isn't knowledgeable andor really doesn't
kind of believe in this but I might be
interested who will I go to um you know
uh how will information get out to the
public and it kind of relates to the
rural issues but you know um speaking
from um our medical aid and dying law
and the implementation over the last
four years and uh I'm with end of life
options New Mexico. Um it's an enormous
challenge um for people to a learn about
um all of these kinds of options as we
approach end of life as well as access
um the resources to um you know perhaps
take advantage of them. And you know, it
sounded like our speaker is part of a
nonprofit that kind of fulfills that
role for Oregon and provides that kind
of information and referrals. And it's
just something I think u Larry and
others that we want to think about. Will
DO play that kind of role once this gets
up and going or is there some other
organization
um that would make sense uh so that
people don't have to struggle to
understand what this is all about?
>> Uh thanks for listening.
>> Thank you Brock. This is actually
Dominic uh from the Department of Health
and I'm putting in the chat right now uh
training the training and education
committee meeting which actually meets
tomorrow afternoon between 1 and 3 and
those are some of the questions that
that committee is going to be tackling
and how that training and education is
going to get out plus as well just
information in general about the program
and the department of course will be
doing some of our own as well. So just
uh so that you know that is uh one of
the things that is coming up and coming
but we have to make plans for it. So
thank you for the question. It's a great
one.
>> Thank you. Uh I'm so sorry. Uh just to
catch up in the chat. Uh Lawrence posted
next meeting of end of life committee is
February 20th from 1 to 3 p.m. Uh Jen
Clemente commented plus one on the
demand generation challenge and thank
you Dominic for posting Friday January
23rd 1 to 3 training and education and
Brenda Burgard is the chair. Uh Lawrence
before I move over to Jen Clemente uh
did you want to go ahead?
Oh. Um, Barrick, you're talking about a
group that, um, I just want to shout out
to your group that has actually been
very active with End of Life and helped
support the bill and that, um, you know,
I I think a lot of us would love to look
up to your group to help um, distribute
information about, uh, the role of this
therapy.
Bareric is part of End of Life New
Mexico, um, which is a group that was
one of the, uh, supporters during the
testimony on the bill.
>> Uh, Bareric, your microphone
credentials.
>> I got it. I I got it. You know, it's and
I'm just going to say it because I feel
it for the last several meetings.
This is a difficult environment to try
and really have conversations. I mean,
it's just difficult. It's clunky to sort
of keep unmuting and muting and we can't
see people. So, it just makes it more
difficult. And I'm sure there's lots of
folks on these sessions that would more
easily be able to contribute um if it
were an even easier environment. I just
had to get that out. But but thank you,
Larry. Um I yeah I don't know to what
degree you know we have our hands full
in trying to work with medical aid and
dying and we don't have a lot of
knowledge about um psilocybin some of
our providers do and some of our
volunteers do but overall
[clears throat] um it's going to take a
lot of education and I guess um you know
Dominic I had thought that that
education and training was really around
sort of provider issues um but I think
you're suggesting that it also perhaps
is around um public education and
outreach um which I did not appreciate.
Again, you guys have a lot going on and
it's it's going to be hard for some of
us who have some related interest to
keep up with it all. I'm just saying
that. But I appreciate the invitation.
Um and I'll try and copy that and see
what tomorrow brings. But I'm glad
you're going to be addressing how the
public is going to begin to absorb this
new uh reality.
>> And and just sort of to to answer that a
little bit, Barack, is two things with
it with regard to we agree that
in-person meetings are necessary. We're
just right now, especially during a
legislative session and in the winter,
this is the best option to ensure that
there's representation from all around
the state and not just from local areas.
For example, the storm that we're all
getting warnings about coming through
here in the next couple of days. Um, and
uh, but for example, some of the other
committees are already looking at
in-person uh, andor hybrid because we
still want to allow people who are not
able to travel to be able to
participate. So we [snorts] do recognize
that it's just the unfortunate timing of
time of the year. The other aspect is uh
so the the training committee is looking
at providers first but then once those
criteria and everything are done
training doesn't stop just with one
particular group of people we need to
figure out how do we get out there and
that's part of why when the bill was
originally done it had that December
28th I'm sorry December 27 timeline so
we would have time to get more
information out so it will be an ongoing
process um and we do appreciate there is
a lot happening. There absolutely is. Um
I if if uh if we could duplicate some of
what we've been doing with about
probably three or four times the number
of people, we still would have more
topics and more areas to to deal
[snorts] with than there are people and
time. Um but with that with regard to
time because we do only have a little
bit of time and Jen has been very
gracious and waiting patiently. So, I'm
just going to uh go over and say uh Jen,
I think it is your turn. And I'm going
to shut up for a minute.
>> Jen, your microphone credentials have
been enabled. You can unmute yourself
and speak whenever you're ready.
>> Thank you so much. Thank you, Dominic.
So, um as some of you know, I wear a few
different hats. One, I'm really
interested in chapency. I've worked as a
chaplain and so I just my perspective
comes from having to you know trying to
push I guess educate make aware of this
issue within my own hospice organization
in Sierra County. And so now putting my
marketing and communications hat back
on. Um one thing that I I really you
know always advise my clients in the
consulting work I do is to find the
persona find the the person who owns the
decision who makes all the big
decisions. And so when I approached
hospice around educating them around
psilocybin medical act back in April,
April, May, June, um the answer came
back, you know, we don't do anything
without the direction of our medical
director. So if I might make a
suggestion, it might be in both, you
know, we have a to cross-pollinate
interest between um this board and the
training and education board and come up
with ways to message and create programs
or education for the medical directors
of the hospices to get the word out.
That might be a a lowest hanging fruit,
if I might use that cliché term,
[laughter]
but yeah, medical directors would be my
first line of persona to reach out to.
That's all I have to say right now.
>> Thank you.
I'll hand it off back over to you,
Lawrence.
>> Great. Thank you. Um, I just wanted to
as a followup to Bareric, um, there is a
lot of interest in the committee in
having an in-person meeting and, uh,
Dominic and I discussed that. My my
thought is we'll probably do that um, in
April when the weather is a little more
reliable for people to um, travel and
the way we would do it is we would have
the the meetings set up wherever we
chose to do that, whether that was
Albuquerque, Santa, or somewhere else,
but we would have it hybrid so people
could participate. But but I think a lot
of us agree that that this can be easier
in conversation than in the little
electronic uh talking squares that we're
dealing with now. So we do plan to have
this committee have an inperson meeting.
>> And so um
>> I'm so sorry. I was just going to say
Jen Clemente in the chat. Takeaway
target hospice medical directors for any
outreach and input. Perhaps a targeted
survey.
>> This is Larry. I just want to thank
everybody. This has been a great
meeting, you know, between Chris and all
the conversation. And uh, you know,
we're getting on two hours. Unless
there's more comments, I think we could
wrap it wrap it up here at this point in
time. We do have a meeting um February
20th. Um Jen is kind enough to offer to
to do a little bit in service there on
the spiritual psychedelic chapency
issue. So we'll have that um which will
be the day after the uh after the
legislature closes and then um we'll
look forward to planning some inperson
meetings. So thanks everybody for all
your great comments and again Chris
thank you for coming to join us.
And thank you everybody.